American Association for Social Security Records 5002
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Unemployment Insurance - Brookwood Conference, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  Invitations to the AASS's second conference on proposed standards for unemployment insurance being held at Brookwood Labor College; requested participants include Dean Sommer of the New York University Law School, Paul Brissenden of Columbia Univ., and Dr. Broadus Mitchell of Johns Hopkins University
- Unemployment Insurance - Maryland, 1933-1938 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  Correspondence with H. O'Conor, Attorney General of Md., and Sen. George Radcliffe re Mr. Epstein's views of the Md. Unemployment Insurance Bill; correspondence with Steven Fitzgerald of The Evening Sun and Simon Sobeloff, Chairman of the Md. Unemployment Insurance Commission, re the Federal Social Security Act and Maryland's own attempts to enact a law; acceptance by Mr. Epstein of an advisory position on the Committee on Unemployment Compensation of the Attorney General Association
- Washington Strategy Conference, 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  Correspondence re a 1944 conference (which never occurred) in which a variety of groups including labor and government, were to meet for an off-the-record discussion of social security
- Unemployment Insurance - North Carolina, 1934-1936 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Correspondence between Mr. Epstein and Prof. Wolff, Executive Secretary of the Unemployment Commission, and T. Wilson, Industrial Commissioner of N.C. re a study of unemployment insurance in N.C.
- Unemployment Insurance - Pennsylvania, 1934-1941 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Correspondence between Mr. Epstein and E. Kelly, Executive Director of Bureau of Employment and Unemployment Compensation in Pennsylvania; includes an article by Kelly on the Stamp plan vs. Payroll tax plan for unemployment insurance
- Unemployment Insurance - Ohio, 1934-1941 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Correspondence between Mr. Epstein and Elizabeth Magee, Executive Secretary of the Consumers League of Ohio re his opinion on Ohio's proposed unemployment bill; routine correspondence
- Unemployment Insurance - Rhode Island, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Correspondence between Mr. Epstein and Clemens France, Chairman of the Division of Unemployment compensation, re experience rating and the interstate hearings on unemployment compensation
- Unemployment Insurance - South Carolina, 1934-1938 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Correspondence between Mr. Epstein and Commissioner Lewis of the S.C. Unemployment Commission re the stamp plan; stamp plan article is enclosed
- Unemployment Insurance - Tennessee, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  Outgoing letter from Epstein to Dr. E. Elberling, Director of Research and Statistics at the Tennessee Unemployment Compensation Division re Elberling's article on statistical analysis of unemployment compensation material
- Unemployment Insurance - Wisconsin, 1937-1940 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  Correspondence between Epstein and a variety of persons re the Nov. 1937 issue of Social Security and its article on unemployment insurance in Wisconsin; correspondence between Epstein and Paul Raushenbaush, Industrial Commission of Wisconsin, re above-mentioned article and his reply
- Unemployment Insurance - States, 1934-1938 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  Requests from the AASS for copies of Oregon's unemployment compensation act and names of the members of the State Unemployment Insurance Committee; replies included; also a requested biographical sketch of the Chief Administrator of the Pennsylvania Unemployment Compensation Law
- Unemployment Insurance State Advisory Council, 1941-1943 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  Routine correspondence; correspondence between Prof. Herman Gray and Lincoln University re the Negro and Social Security
- Unemployment Insurance - Misc., 1932-1938 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  Correspondence
- Unemployment Insurance - New York, 1934-1942 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Correspondence re the Byrnes-Condon Bill and changes suggested by the AASS; correspondence between Mr. Epstein and N. Stone re "An American Plan for Unemployment Reserve Funds"; correspondence between Mr. Epstein and George Meany re unemployment insurance in New York State
- Wagner-Murray-Dingell-Altmeyer, 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  Important correspondence re the new role of the AASS in the 1940's under Harvey Lebrun, and individual's ideas on social security
- Miscellaneous, 1937-1941 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  Routine correspondence re state unemployment laws, etc.; respondents included A. Altmeyer of the Social Security Board in Washington, and letters from Gov. Saltonstall's (Mass.) office; also a guest list for the Abraham Epstein dinner
- Watt, Robert J., 1944 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  Outgoing letter from Harvey Lebrun to the AFL
- Weir, Joseph P.B., 1934-1936 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Welch, Margaret, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  Correspondence between Epstein and a Consumer's group
- West, P.R., 1934 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  Incoming letter to the AASS re unemployment insurance
- Weisman, Margaret (Executive Secretary of the Consumer's League of Massachusetts), 1934-1942 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  Correspondence re unemployment legislation, conferences, health insurance
- Wise, Stephen S., 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Witte, Edwin E. (Committee on Economic Security), 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  Correspondence between Epstein and M. Schnopper of the Committee; correspondence with Barbara Armstrong, Frances Perkins, Douglas Brown re Epstein's views and role in the work of the Committee; also the Committee's staff report on unemployment insurance
- Workmen's Compensation, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  Outgoing letter from Lebrun re the possible amalgamation between the AASS and the AALL, with an enclosed editorial from Social Security about the possibilities
- Workmen's Compensation News, 1942-1943 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  Enclosure re advances in workmen's compensation during 1942-43; correspondence between Lebrun and various state industrial commissions re changes in workmen's compensation during 1943, with enclosures of new laws
- Workmen's Sickness and Death Benefit Fund, 1934-1943 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  Correspondence between Epstein and Paul Sturm, National Secretary, WSDBF, mainly re contributions to the AASS and attending meetings of WSDBF
- Wunderlich, Frieda, 1934-1944 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  General correspondence
- Wadsworth, James J. (Assemblyman, NYS), 1936 (Box 6, Folder 11a)
  re Social Security Program opposition
- New York City, 1929-1942 (Box 7, Folder All)
  Books and pamphlets outlining New York City's public assistance programs (unemployment relief, aid for the aged, etc.); also, reports from the Department of Welfare of New York City, and other committees
- New York State, 1929-1942 (Box 8, Folder All)
  Pamphlets, reports and books describing public assistance programs in New York State (unemployment insurance, old age relief, and the history of public assistance in New York are some of the topics included in this box
- New York State, 1929-1950 (Box 9, Folder All)
  Printed materials on unemployment in New York State - contains minutes of meetings of the Joint Legislative Committee on Unemployment, training manuals for employment office workers, and material on old age
- Other States, 1935-1941 (Box 10, Folder All)
  Reports on unemployment compensation in various states (i.e. Oregon, Alabama, Wisconsin, etc.) dealing with topics including experience rating and seasonal unemployment; folders, reports, and books
- Other States (Box 11, Folder All)
  Reports on unemployment insurance and experience rating from various states. the federal government
- U.S. Dept. of Labor, Children's Bureau, Youth Administration, 1932-1940 (Box 12, Folder All)
  Books, reports, and pamphlets re social security and the security of children (i.e. the effects of unemployment on children and young people)
- Card Index to State Social Security Bills (Box 35, Folder All)
- Bibliography (Box 36, Folder All)
- U.S. Federal Emergency Relief Administration, 1934-1936 (Box 13, Folder All)
  Research bulletins from this body
- U.S. Government Publications Relating to Social Security, 1933-1943 (Box 14, Folder All)
  Contains pamphlets and printed materials from the government re social security
- U.S. National Resources Planning Board, 1937-1942 (Box 15, Folder All)
  Contains reports on urban planning, transportation, the stabilization of employment, and other issues investigated by the NRPB
- U.S. National Resources Planning Board, National Resources Planning Committee, National Health Conference, National Health Survey, 1933-1938 (Box 16, Folder All)
  Contains health surveys and various reports on the economic effects of expenditures on federal works programs along with other types of expenditures (i.e. consumer spending)
- U.S. Federal Security Agency, Social Security Board - Statistics of Family Composition in Selected Areas of the U.S, 1934-1936 (Box 17, Folder All)
  Contains reports entitled "Statistics of Family Composition" for various areas of the U.S.
- U.S. Social Security Board, 1937-1942 (Box 18, Folder All)
  Handbooks, pamphlets, and reports on aspects of the Social Security Act (i.e. old age pensions, unemployment compensation, etc.); also, a claims manual is included
- U.S. Works Projects Administration, 1932-1937 (Box 19, Folder All)
  Reports on WPA projects and many handbooks on unemployment in the U.S.
- Foreign Countries - British, 1911-1940 (Box 20, Folder All)
  Reports, articles, and handbooks on unemployment compensation, old-age pensions plans, national health insurance, etc.; reports from the Ministry of Labor
- Foreign Countries, 1909-1940 (Box 21, Folder All)
  Contains handbooks on public assistance from various countries (i.e. Canada, Chile, Germany, etc.) - some are in foreign languages
- Economics Policy, 1931-1942 (Box 22, Folder All)
  Handbooks and pamphlets on many varied economic topics - unemployment compensation In the U.S., German economic policy in Europe, preventing economic depressions, credit for consumers, etc
- Health Insurance - State Health Legislation Introduced, 1937-1941 (Box 23, Folder 15)
  Newspaper clippings and printed materials re the compulsory health insurance debate; copies of the Association's Model Bill for compulsory health insurance are included
- Health Insurance - Medical Profession, 1932-1940 (Box 23, Folder 14)
  Newspaper clippings and printed materials on the health insurance controversy - the AMA opposed to compulsory health insurance, and the AASS in favor of it
- Health Insurance - Kingsbury, John A, 1935 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  Letter, speeches, and clippings re former NYC commissioner of charities and his campaign for compulsory health insurance
- Health Insurance - Illness, Extent and Cost Of, 1933-1941 (Box 23, Folder 12-12a)
  Subject files, mainly speeches, with clippings and reprints
- Health Insurance - Hospital Conditions and Finance, 1930-1941 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  Subject files, mainly news releases, articles and clippings, 3 folders
- Health Insurance - Federal Government, 1938-1941 (Box 23, Folder 10)
  Subject files containing mainly newspaper clippings, with occasional articles, news releases, and health insurance schemes introduced into Congress
- Health Insurance - Corlears Hook Medical Association, 1942 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  Two year report on an experiment in volunteer pre-paid medical care for low income families in NYC
- Health Insurance - Conference, 1940 (Box 23, Folder 8)
  Contains a list of persons invited to attend this conference which will consider revisions in the Health Insurance Bill; also, a list of those who accepted invitation
- Health Insurance - Conference, 1939 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  Misc. Documents. Includes lists of individuals invited to attend the conference, and those that actually came
- Health Insurance - Conference, 1934 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  List of persons attending 1934 health insurance conference in which suggestions for a model bill were drafted; also, a list of individuals to whom the bill was sent
- Health Insurance - California, 1934-1935 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  Newspaper clippings; corrected typescript entitled "Interest in Health Insurance Reassuring"
- Health Insurance - Bureau of Cooperative Medicine, 1939 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  News releases and bulletins
- Health - Bibliography, 1938-1941 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  Bibliographies and book reviews of books and pamphlets re health insurance; for correspondence re books see box #2 Health-Bibliography
- Health Bill - Assoc. Model, 1934 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  Includes "Basic Principles for a Health Insurance Bill" formulated at a 1934 conference of experts under the auspices of the AASS; also, related comments, notes, and revisions
- Health Insurance Bill - Assoc. Model, 1940 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  Draft of the model bill, speeches, essays, analysis
- Health Insurance Under Social Security Act, 1936-1941 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  Newspaper clippings and printed articles describing the types of health programs now made available to states under the Federal Social Security Act
- Health Insurance & Medical Profession - State and Local, 1935-1936 (Box 24, Folder 2-2a)
  Includes printed material on various aspects of insurance and the medical profession (state and local)
- Health Insurance - Miscellaneous Material, 1941 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  Includes printed materials; the speech "Health Insurance for Connecticut" by Alfred Bingham, a member of the State Senate,; paper by Robert Watt entitled "Health Insurance"; an address by Robert J. Wagner; an address by Bertram Bernheim
- Health Insurance - Miscellaneous Material, 1938-1941 (Box 24, Folder 4-4a)
  Includes printed material, clippings
- Health Insurance - Misc. Individuals - Organizations, 1931-1939 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  Clippings, report, printed articles
- Health Insurance - New York, 1942-1943 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  Includes clippings, notes; also, "Health Insurance Plan for State of NY" by Clement Conoli, Deputy Industrial Commissioner
- Health Insurance & Medical Profession -Individuals, 1932-1940 (Box 24, Folder 1-1a)
  Clippings, printed materials, correspondence; a recommendation for Wendell Wilkie from John Peters, M.D.; proposals for the improvement of medical care from a committee of physicians to Mr. Epstein; and address by M. Tobias
- Health Insurance - States, 1943 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  Envelopes of clippings, pamphlets, and bills re Oregon, "Delaware, Washington, New Hampshire, and District of Columbia
- Health Insurance - Wagner Bill - Opposition, 1941-1943 (Box 24, Folder 16)
  Clippings
- Health Insurance - Labor, 1942-1943 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  Newspaper clippings and printed articles on labor-management negotiated health plans (i.e. Textile Workers); William Green's (Pres. AFL) promotion of programs to increase social insurance (i.e. workmen's compensation, disability programs)
- Health Insurance - Substitutes for Voluntary Schemes, etc, 1929-1940 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  Pamphlets, reports, tables, releases
- Health Insurance - Medical Care Plans - Hospital Care Plans, 1942-1943 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  Includes printed materials
- Health Insurance - Wagner Bill - General Opposition to Health Insurance - Features of, 1943 (Box 24, Folder 13)
- Health Insurance - Wagner Bill - Opposition from Insurance Companies, 1942-1943 (Box 24, Folder 14)
- Health Insurance - Wagner Bill - Medical Opposition, 1941-1943 (Box 24, Folder 15)
  Clippings, publications, notes
- Health Insurance - Rhode Island, 1941-1943 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  Pamphlets, clippings
- Health Insurance - Miscellaneous Publications, 1930-1945 (Box 25)
  Publications on health insurance
- Old Age Assistance, 1930-1945 (Box 26)
  Publications on old age programs
- Old Age Pensions - Industrial Plans, 1924-1935 (Box 27, Folder 12-12a)
- Old Age Pensions - Abroad - General, 1925-1932 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  Clippings, articles, "Brief Report of Findings Abroad" (5 p. mss.), pamphlets
- Old Age Pensions - Citizenship, 1937 (Box 27, Folder 3)
- Old Age Pensions - Complaints, 1927-1934 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  Clippings, reports, articles, "Old Age Assistance Amendment to Constitution", speech by Harry A. McKey, City Treasurer of Philadelphia (3 p. mss.)
- Old Age Pensions - Contributory, 1934 (Box 27, Folder 5)
  Clippings, pamphlet
- Old Age Pensions - General, 1928-1931 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  Clippings, articles
- Old Age Pensions - General, 1934-1940 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  Articles, chart, clippings
- Old Age Pensions - Human Interest, 1935-1942 (Box 27, Folder 8)
- Old Age Pensions - Industrial Plans, 1928-1932 (Box 27, Folder 9-9a)
  Pamphlets, chart, articles
- Old Age, Middle Age, Employment - Handicaps, etc, 1928-1941 (Box 27, Folder 1-1a)
  Publications, releases, bibliography, clippings, articles, questionnaire; articles include "Aged Women Swamp Relief Rolls"; notes on AMA meeting re employment for the aged; proposed study of the age factor in industry; excerpts from a NAM meeting
- Old Age Pensions - Industrial Plans, 1924-1926 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  Clippings, pamphlets
- Old Age Pensions - Various Schemes, 1930-1933 (Box 27, Folder 21)
  Clippings; memo entitled "Old Age Security, By an Educational Birth Tax" by Saul Wiland (attorney, NYC)
- Old Age Pensions - News, 1930-1931 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  Stories on Assn. Clippings
- Old Age Pensions - Private Organizations, Church, School, 1927-1936 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  Printed materials, clippings
- Old Age Pensions - Organization of the Aged, 1938 (Box 27, Folder 15)
  One article
- Old Age Pensions - Public Employees Retirement Systems, 1932-1941 (Box 27, Folder 16)
- Old Age Pensions - Railroad Retirement Act, 1935-1938 (Box 27, Folder 17-17a)
- Old Age Pensions - Relief - Almshouses, 1940-1941 (Box 27, Folder 18)
- Old Age Pensions - "Streamlining" Trends, 1938-1941 (Box 27, Folder 19)
- Old Age Pensions - Trade Union Pension Plans, 1927-1933 (Box 27, Folder 20)
  Clippings; Pensions plans from Lithographers, Iron Workers, Granite Cutters, Trainmen, Bricklayers, and Typographical Union
- Old Age Pensions - Industrial Plans, 1922-1932 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  Pamphlets re various plans
- Public Assistance, 1931-1940 (Box 28)
  Booklets and reports re public relief programs in various states - Illinois, Missouri, Pennsylvania, etc.
- Social Security Board - Employees, 1936-1938 (Box 29, Folder 17)
  Clippings, releases
- Railroad Retirement Act, 1939-1942 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  Publications, bills
- Social Security Act (Federal), 1934-1943 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  Printed hearings, reports, bills, and publications
- Social Security Act (Federal), 1935-1940 (Box 29, Folder 4)
- Social Security Act (Federal) - Advisory Council for Employment Security, 1940-1942 (Box 29, Folder 5-6)
  Releases
- Social Security Act (Federal) - Altmeyer, Chmn. of Social Security Board, 1943 (Box 29, Folder 7)
- Social Security Act (Federal) - Amendments, 1941-1942 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  President's 1941 Suggestions SSB federalization proposal and press reaction
- Social Security Amendments, 1939-1940 (Box 29, Folder 9)
  Articles, clippings, releases, pamphlets
- Social Security - American Beveridge Report, 1942-1943 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  Clippings, nine page report
- Social Security - Analysis by Different Persons, 1936-1940 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  Clippings, articles, address, newsletter of the National League of Women Voters, memo from YWCA
- Social Security - Annuities - Voluntary, 1939-1940 (Box 29, Folder 12)
- Social Security - Appropriations, Expenditures, Reserves, etc., 1936-1942 (Box 29, Folder 13)
  Clippings, statements, releases, GPO Documents
- Social Security - Armed Forces, 1943 (Box 29, Folder 14)
- Railroad Unemployment Insurance Act, 1940-1941 (Box 29, Folder 1)
- Social Security Board - Administration, Problems, Procedures, etc., 1938-1939 (Box 29, Folder 16)
  Publications, articles, clippings, address by A.J. Altmeyer
- Social Security - Cost of Administration, 1937-1938 (Box 29, Folder 30)
- Social Security Board - Federal Advisory Council, 1940 (Box 29, Folder 18)
  Memos, releases, statements
- Social Security - Green, Senator, 1943 (Box 29, Folder 19)
  Clippings, legislative bill re Sen Green's proposal for expansion of the social security system
- Social Security - Social Security Board Machinery, Methods, etc, 1937-1940 (Box 29, Folder 20)
  Clippings, article
- Social Security - Social Security Board - Offices, Space, Buildings, etc, 1936-1940 (Box 29, Folder 21)
- Social Security - Social Security Board Regional Offices, 1943 (Box 29, Folder 22)
- Social Security - Business, 1936-1942 (Box 29, Folder 23)
  Clippings, addresses, publications, releases, articles
- Social Security - Byrnes Committee Report, 1939 (Box 29, Folder 24)
- Social Security - Civilian War Relief, 1942 (Box 29, Folder 25)
  Legislative bills, notes, clippings
- Social Security - Committees and Special Groups, 1936-1938 (Box 29, Folder 26)
  Clippings, articles, releases, statement
- Social Security - Conferences, 1935-1939 (Box 29, Folder 27)
  Releases, program, clippings
- Social Security - Confusion, 1935-1940 (Box 29, Folder 28)
- Social Security - Congressional Pensions, 1939-1942 (Box 29, Folder 29)
- Social Security - Bane, Frank, 1936-1938 (Box 29, Folder 15)
  Bane, Ex-Director of the SSB resigns; clippings releases, articles, addresses
- Social Security - Eliot Bill, 1940-1942 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  Clippings, bill, notes
- Social Security - Defense Releases, 1940-1942 (Box 30, Folder 1-1a)
  Clippings, publications, transcript of interview with William Hudson, Commissioner of Welfare (NYC)
- Social Security - Internal Revenue Bureau -Tax and Rulings, 1936-1940 (Box 30, Folder 18)
  Publications, clippings
- Social Security - Imberman, A. A., 1936-1937 (Box 30, Folder 17)
- Social Security - Hoey,Jane M., 1936-1938 (Box 30, Folder 16)
- Social Security - Grants-In-Aid, 1936-1941 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  Clippings, articles, pamphlet
- Social Security - Foreign Opinion, 1937 (Box 30, Folder 14)
  Clipping
- Social Security - Federalism and Federalization, 1940-1942 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  Questionnaire notes, articles, clippings
- Social Security - Life Insurance, 1936-1941 (Box 30, Folder 20)
  Clippings, publications
- Social Security - Employment Service, 1941-1942 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  Clippings, Article, releases
- Social Security - McNutt, Paul V., 1939-1940 (Box 30, Folder 21)
  Clippings, address, releases, article, testimony
- Social Security - Effects on State Legislation, 1935-1936 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  Clippings, editorials, issue of Congressional intelligence
- Social Security - Effects, 1936-1940 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  Articles, address
- Social Security - Editorials Urging General Taxation for Social Security, 1936-1939 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  clippings
- Social Security - Downey Committee (Universal Pensions), 1941 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  Statement by A.J. Altmeyer, Chairman, Social Security Board
- Social Security - Douglas, Paul H., 1936-1940 (Box 30, Folder 5)
- Social Security - Disability Permanent, 1940 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  Articles, typed mss.
- Social Security - Dewson, Mary, 1937 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  Clippings, releases re Dewson "Discusses Social Security from Women's Viewpoint"
- Social Security - Defense and Financing -Morganthau Proposals, 1941 (Box 30, Folder 2)
- Social Security - Employers Questionnaires, 1937-1938 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  Articles, clippings
- Social Security - Pamphlets of Social Security Board, 1936-1938 (Box 30, Folder 30)
  Pamphlets, clippings, releases
- Social Security - Relief and Security Statistics, 1936-1937 (Box 30, Folder 39)
  Publications
- Social Security - Relief, 1937-1943 (Box 30, Folder 38)
  Clippings, statement, bill, testimony of demons France, Dir. State Dept. of Social Welfare, Rhode Island
- Social Security - Registration of Workers, 1936-1931 (Box 30, Folder 37)
  Releases, clippings, 5 p. mss. by Epstein re unemployment insurance